# CHUKWUMA HILARY AKPU

+447769380756 | <u>holaryc@gmail.com</u> <u>github.com/hilariie</u> | <u>linkedin.com/in/hilary-ml-engineer</u>

#### **PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY**

An experienced data scientist with 4 years of work experience applying data science to business applications. Particularly experienced in developing and deploying high-performing machine learning and deep learning models to solve business problems. I am rooted in the pursuit of impacting lives and businesses through my experience and skills by developing solutions founded on data.

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

**Machine Learning:** Logistic/linear regression, random forest trees, K-means, gradient boosted trees. **Deep Learning:** Natural language processing, Convolutional Neural Network, BERT (LLMs), VGG16, Transformers, GPT, Whisper, SAM, YOLO, DeepSORT, Image segmentation.

**Libraries:** NumPy, Pandas, Scikit-learn, Matplotlib, Seaborn, ggplot, TensorFlow, Beautiful Soup, Scrapy.

**Programming:** Python, R, Object-oriented programming, SQL, Version Control (Git), CI/CD, unit testing, APIs.

**Tools and Technologies:** Apache Airflow, Microsoft Azure (Databricks, Data Factory), KNIME, Microsoft Excel, Docker, Anaconda, PyCharm, Apache Spark, Hadoop, PowerBI, Octoparse.

Database: Snowflake, PostgreSQL, CouchDB (NoSQL).

## **WORK EXPERIENCE**

## Research Volunteer • University of Reading

Jun. 2023 – Present

- In collaboration with UK scientists, I developed a multi-object tracking and analysis system using YOLO and DeepSORT that provides valuable soil information. (*github link*)
- Working on publishing a paper on the automated tracking and analysis system I developed.
- Researched, proposed, and implemented modifications to state-of-the-art algorithms.
- Developed an audio transcriber using OpenAI's Whisper and GPT models to help people in rural areas get better access to vital information. (github link)
- Developed algorithms that distinguished between male/female animals and detected mating occurrences in a video using image segmentation coordinates and the Euclidean Distance metric.
- Utilized adaptive thresholding and the Segment Anything Model for precise image segmentation.
- Annotated 500+ images for image detection model training.

#### Data Scientist • Reliance HMO

Jun. 2022 – Oct. 2022

- Trained BERT and sequential (CNN for text) models to classify diagnoses with an accuracy above 90%. This improved the labelling rate by 10% and provided a foundation for improving the pricing model to reduce loss. This also brought to light discrepancies in the data that were otherwise hidden.
- Led the pre-processing of a large text dataset using techniques such as lemmatization, stemming, and regex pattern matching.
- Developed a labelling algorithm to accurately label a healthcare dataset, resulting in a 70% labelling rate.
- Spearheaded the development of a user-friendly application to access the pricing model prototype using CSS, HTML, and Python.
- Executed data engineering tasks on Snowflake using SQL queries.
- Leveraged PowerBI to analyze and visualize insights, providing valuable information for executive decision-making.

- Conducted advanced customer segmentation (B2B) using firmographic segmentation and tiering, boosting customer satisfaction.
- Successfully migrated a database from CouchDB to PostgreSQL for an application by rearchitecting the codebase and executing data engineering tasks on unstructured data.
- Developed a notification system for a mobile app, increasing vaccination rates by 25%.
- Automated staff productivity tracking process, reducing manual input by 100%.
- Conducted data collection, pre-processing, and automation using Apache Airflow on Docker.

## Data Analyst • Softcom Limited

Apr. 2019 - Oct. 2020

• Conducted rigorous data analysis and created reports using Power BI, Excel, and other data visualization tools to support business decisions.

#### **EDUCATION**

**MSc Data Science** – University of Reading – Reading, England.

Sep. 2022 – Sep. 2023

- Graduated with a Distinction.
- Big Data: Developed and deployed machine learning models on Azure and PySpark.
- Cloud Computing: Developed a concurrent MapReduce algorithm without relying on Hadoop (github link).
- Mathematics and Statistics: Deepened my understanding of the foundational and statistical aspects of data science.
- Data ethics and security

**BSc Computer Science** – Mountain Top University – Ogun, Nigeria.

Oct. 2016 – Dec. 2020

- GPA 4.48/5.0.
- Completed a dissertation on using machine learning models for diagnosing heart disease with an accuracy above 90%.

## Computer vision Nanodegree – Udacity.

Sep. 2020

- Developed a CNN model to detect key points on the face.
- Developed an encoder-decoder model that generates captions for images.

#### PERSONAL PROJECTS

## **Multi-object tracking**

May 2023

• Developed a program using image segmentation and OpenCV's tracking algorithms, to track multiple objects in a video. (*github link*)

## Python emailing package

Mar. 2022

• Designed and developed a comprehensive Python package that simplifies the process of sending emails, achieving over 8,000 downloads in a year. (github link)

## **Multi-output Neural Network**

May 2023

• Developed a system to simplify the implementation of the one-vs-all approach on multiclass image problems. I made modifications to classes and functions from the TensorFlow library indicative of an improved understanding of the library and neural network in general. (github link)